Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5204 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- August 1948 to December 1948, Undated 1948, and Miscellaneous Union Business 1948. (Reel 33)
  - December, 1948, 5 (Reel 33)
    There is a copy of a letter from Hank Hasiwar to both the Federal and the California State Mediation Service, asking them to intervene in the Di Giorgio strike (3), a letter from strike leader James B. Price on the current situation (29), and a report entitled "The Present Status of Federal Farm Labor Camps in California" prepared by California State Senator Harry E. Drobish, along with a copy of his covering letter to Cong. Helen Gahagan Douglas (31)
  - No Date, 1948, 6 (Reel 33)
    Agreements between the NFLU and the H.J. Heinz Co. and the Imperial Agricultural Corp. of Hartford, Conn.; Statement of C.J. Haggerty, Secretary-Treasurer of the California State Federation of Labor, before the House Committee on Agriculture; copy of "Agreement in Relation to the Employment of Jamaicans in Agricultural Work in the Sugar Industry in the United States of America"; materials relating to the Di Giorgio strike, including press releases, appeals to other unions for strike funds, a chronological summary of the strike up to Feb. 12, 1948, and background information sheets on the Di Giorgio company
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1948, 7 (Reel 33)
    Folder 1181 -- Applications for Work, 1948 (Approx. 400 forms). Folder 1184 -- Shipping lists and Worker's Contracts for jobs with the H.J. Heinz Co. All shipping lists filmed. Two different contracts were used, and one sample of each type of contract has been filmed.
- January 1949 to December 1949, Undated 1949, Miscellaneous Union Business 1949, and January 1950 to March 1950. (Reel 34)
  - January to March, 1949, 1 (Reel 34)
    a major topic is the US-Mexican International Executive Agreement for the importation of Mexican contract workers (or braceros) into the United States; see especially two lengthy NLFU memoranda on this subject (Jan 8, 10) a draft copy of the Agreement and individual work contract (Jan 3), and two letters from Galarza on why the details of the Agreement had not been made public (March 15,16). The NFLU began an intensive drive to obtain legislation to improve the lot of farm workers during February; the papers include a letter from Mitchell to NSF Executive Secretary Hazel Whitman outlining plans for the campaign (Jan 6), a letter sent to all US Senators on the first of February containing the union's proposals, replies from the Senators (appear throughout February), and statements by Mitchell on the need for housing for migratory labor and on the use of the Taft-Hartley Act to break the Di Giorgio strike (Feb 18; March 6). On the legal cases arising from the Di Giorgio strike, see the correspondence from lawyer Alexander H. Schullman. An apparently complete list of secretaries of NFLU locals appears on February 17
  - April to June, 1949, 2 (Reel 34)
    As the union's legislative campaign continued, Mitchell testified before Congress on minimum wages and social security for farm workers and on rural housing (April 14, 20, 26). On the California situation, see two letters from Alexander H. Schullman concerning the Di Giorgio injunction suit (April 1, 28), the minutes of a meeting of the California NFLU Organizing Committee (May 15), and a memorandum from Mitchell to Cong. Leonard Irving on a proposed investigation of farm labor by the House Education and Labor Committee (June 30). There is an exchange between Mitchell and Rev. Johnnie F. Moore on the difficulties of organizing Florida citrus works (May 17, 24), and another exchange between Mitchell and Roger N. Baldwin on the quality of the work of Ernesto Galarza (June 9,10). Also on June 9, the reader will find a copy of an extremely important report by George I. Sanchez and Lyle Sounders of the University of Texas entitled "Wetbacks"
  - July to September, 1949, 3 (Reel 34)
    The International Executive Agreement with Mexico was signed on August 1; the papers include a 12-page analysis of the pact by Galarza (Aug. 15) and an exchange between Mitchell and USES Director Robert C. Goodwin on the bracero program (Aug. 22; Sept. 19). On the NFLU legislative program, see especially a letter from Alabama Congressman George Grant on H.R. 5557 (July 15), and a detailed letter from Mitchell to Cong. Helen Gahagan Douglas on the various proposals before Congress concerning farm wages (Aug. 11). The overwhelming topic in the papers for September is the NFLU strike of 30,000 cotton pickers in the San Joaquin Valley in California. In addition to the numerous telegrams and press releases on the strike throughout the lengthy report which appear during October (Oct. 3,20). There is also a mimeographed copy of a letter from Mitchell to President Truman, requesting him to appoint a Presidential Commission to investigate the plight of the nation's farm workers (Sept 28)
  - October to December, 1949, 4 (Reel 34)
    The House Education and Labor Committee held hearings on the Di Giorgio strike in Bakersfield, California from November 12 to 14; the papers include an exchange between Mitchell and Alexander Schullman on the hearings (Oct 24,26), the NFLU brief, a nine-page report on the strike, a statement by Schullman, and an anti-union statement by Hank L. Strobel, a Monterey County grower (all filed at Nov. 12). The Di Giorgio Fruit Corporation filed a $2 million libel suit against the NFLU based on the film, "Poverty in the Valley of Plenty". On the libel suit, see the Complaint filed by the company (Oct 28), and a detailed letter from Schullman (Nov. 18). There are also two letters from Schullman on the union's victory in the Di Giorgio injunction case (Dec 27, 30). In mid-December, Mitchell succeeded in convincing the Advisory Council of the Bureau of Employment Security to go on record as opposed to the importation of foreign nationals for farm work; his lengthy statement to the Council appears in the papers (Dec. 14)
  - No Date, 1949, 5 (Reel 34)
    Memorandum, "Proposals for Revising and Bringing Up to Date H.R. 3856"; report on "Farm Labor and Farm Labor Housing"; AF of L statement on "Including Costs of Hired Farm Labor in the Parity Price Index"; pamphlets, leaflets, etc., printed in Spanish to explain the work of the NFLU to Mexican-Americans.
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1949, 6 (Reel 34)
    Folder 1231 -- Petitions on the importation of Mexican Nationals, signed chiefly by NFLU members in Missouri. One sample filmed
  - January to March, 1950, 7 (Reel 34)
    The Sixteenth Annual Convention was held at Fresno, California from January 13 to 15; the papers include the complete Proceedings, and the amended Constitution. There are a number of letters, press releases, and reports from Galarza throughout this period on the problems of 100,000 unemployed farm workers in California; see especially his radio address on this subject (March 28). A majority report of the House Education and Labor Sub-Committee on the Di Giorgio strike issued over the signature of Cong. Richard M. Nixon appears on March 9; the minority report appears in the undated section at the end of 1950. On Nixon's role in writing the report, see a letter from Alexander Schullman to Mitchell (March 18). There is a seven-page report from California organizer Hank Hasiwar on the Imperial Valley (Jan. 25) and an exchange between Mitchell and Schullman about setting up a voter registration drive among Florida citrus workers to aid the re-election of Senator Claude Pepper (March 6, 9).
- April 1950 to December 1950, Undated 1950, and January 1951 to June 1951. (Reel 35)
  - April to June, 1950, 1 (Reel 35)
    The operation of the US Employment Service in California is the main topic in the papers for this Spring. See especially the long reports on NFLU organization in California is the main topic in the papers for this Spring. See especially the long reports on NFLU organization in California from staff members Galarza, Hasiwar, and Becker (April 6, 7, 10, n.d.), and an exchange between Mitchell and both Secretary of Labor Maurice J. Tobin and USES Director Robert C. Goodwin on the bracero problem in California (April 21; May 26,29; June 6). There is much detailed information on the California organizational set-up in the papers for June, including a report on the new membership drive in each local (June 1,2,15). The libel suit filed by the Di Giorgio Corporation against the union was settled in return for agreement to end the strike; see the copies of the legal agreement (May 8, 23) and a letter from Alexander Schullman to Mitchell on this subject (April 21). Throughout the year, the NFLU was involved in a dispute with the National Farmers' Union over the organization of dairy farmers in New York, Louisiana, and other states. For information on the dispute see Mitchell to NSF Executive Secretary Beth Biderman (April 6)
  - July and August, 1950, 2 (Reel 35)
    The President's Commission on Migrant Labor began to hold hearings on July 13; the papers include statements by the National Consumers League and the CIO (July 13), the NFLU (July 14), and a lengthy statement by Ernesto Galarza entitled "American and Foreign Farm Workers in California" (August 12). See also the letters from Mitchell to his organizers advising them on a strategy in dealing with the Commission (July 21, 25), and a letter from Texas organizer George F. Webber describing his testimony during the El Paso hearings (August 8)
  - September and October, 1950, 3 (Reel 35)
    The union called a strike of 3,500 tomato pickers at Tracy, California during September; the progress of the strike may be followed in the letters and telegrams from Ernesto Galarza. An NFLU strike which involved 20,000 California cotton pickers took place in October, but the only information on it appears in a press release announcing the settlement of the strike (Oct 30). Other items of special interest include: an NFLU Farm Labor Supply Agreement (Sept 7); a letter from Secretary of State Dean Acheson to William Green on the farm labor agreement with Mexico (Sept 18); and a memorandum from Mitchell to USES on "The Refusal of Employers to Accept American Agricultural Workers for Employment" (Sept. 27)
  - November and December, 1950, 4 (Reel 35)
    There is a great deal of correspondence from Ernesto Galarza, including two letters to Dr. Varden Fuller of the President's Commission on Migrant Labor on the Mexican immigration problem (Nov. 28, 30) and a long report on the Imperial Valley (Dec. 31). The papers include a report by Rev. Arthur C. Churchill on his work as Minister to Farm Labor in the Mid-South (Nov. 18), and the testimony of Mitchell to an unidentified government loyalty board on behalf of Val Lorwin (Dec. 20).
  - No Date, 1950, 5 (Reel 35)
    "The Condition of Farm Workers in 1950", a report by NSF Executive Secretary Beth Biderman; NFLU pamphlet, "A Letter to Shed Workers Affiliated with FTA"; exhibits submitted to the President's Commission on Migrant Labor; statements to the President's Commission by Leon B. Schachter and William Green; minority report of the Sub-Committee of the House Education and Labor Committee investigating the Di Giorgio strike; draft o fNFLU local union by-laws; "Analysis of Work Performed by Organizers Assigned by A.F. of L. to NFLU"; summary of monthly reports of NFLU locals in the Mid-South during 1950; correspondence from Ernesto Galarza; activity report of NFLU Puerto Rico organizer Carl S. Lara
  - January and February, 1951, 6 (Reel 35)
    Negotiations between the United States and Mexico on the renewal of the International Executive Agreement on Migratory Labor began on January 26; on this subject, see the detailed reports from Ernesto Galarza in Mexico City (Jan. 27 to Feb. 12) and two NFLU press releases (Jan 26; Feb. 7). A massive NFLU organizing drive began in the Imperial Valley of California; see especially an exchange between Mitchell and Galarza on strategy (Jan 10, 17), and letters from organizer Hank Hasiwar to the Department of Labor on violations of the Mexican Agreement by Imperial Valley growers (Feb 5, 8). There is a report from F.T. Riley on a non-NFLU strike of 5,000 Florida fruit pickers (Feb. 2; note: newspaper clippings pasted to the report have been blocked out), and two letters from Hasiwar on his temporary assignment re-organizing the Louisiana Fruit and Vegetable Producers Union (Feb. 21, 28)
  - March and April, 1951, 7 (Reel 35)
    The papers contain an abundance of material on the Imperial Valley campaign, including: a lengthy report by Galarza on the Valley (March 12); a report listing the individual growers accused of violating the US-Mexican Agreement, with attached correspondence between the NFLU and various government officials on the problem (March 29); and an NFLU press release on the union's demands to the Imperial Valley Farmers Association (April 27). There are reports from Galarza and Texas organizer George F. Webber on their attempts to make contact with Mexican unions to help stop the "wetback" flow (March 9; April 5). The President's Commission on Migratory Labor released its report during April; the report itself does not appear in the papers, but there is an NFLU press release on it and a letter from Mitchell to his staff on getting the Commission's recommendations implemented (April 9)
  - May and June, 1951, 8 (Reel 35)
    From May 23 to June 25, the NFLU led a strike of 6,000 fruit and vegetable workers in the Imperial Valley in an effort to win collective bargaining and an end to the exploitation of "wetback" labor. A voluminous number of letters, telegrams, and press releases throughout both months details the progress of the strike. The failure of the Department of Labor to remove "wetbacks" who were serving as strikebreakers became a major issue in the strike. Documents of special interest include: a copy of a legal complaint filed by the NFLU against the Department of Labor to force the Department to remove all Mexican Nationals from the strike area (May 31); a seven-page confidential memorandum by Hank Hasiwar on the "Operation of s of the NFLU in the Imperial Valley, February-May, 1951" (n.d. [May]); a long letter from Mitchell to the Department of Labor, accusing it of acting as "an employment agency for strikebreakers" (June 25); and a 23-page NFLU report entitled "The Wetback Strike" (filed at June 25). In addition to the Imperial Valley strike, there are two memoranda by organizer Bill Becker on "Imported Labor in the Salinas Valley" (May 4,11).
- July 1951 to December 1951, Undated 1951, January 1952 to December 1952, Undated 1952, and Miscellaneous Union Business 1952. (Reel 36)
  - July to September, 1951, 1 (Reel 36)
    The papers include: a memorandum from Mitchell to his organizing staff on future plans for the union (July 3); the minutes of the NFLU San Joaquin Valley Council (July 8); an exchange between Mitchell and Roger Baldwin reviewing the work of Ernesto Galarza (July 19, 26); the full proceedings of the NFLU California State Convention (Sept. 14); and a letter from California lawyer Alexander H. Schullman on ways of dealing with the US Wage Stabilization Board, which had announced a ceiling on the wages of cotton pickers (Sept. 17)
  - October, 1951, 2 (Reel 36)
    Items of special interest include a report from Galarza on an arrangement for joint membership worked out with the Alianza Ncional de Braceros de Mexico (2), and a copy of a letter from Ed S. Miller of the Hotel and Restaurant Worker's Union to Schenley Industries, Inc., threatening a boycott of Schenley products if the company does not resume bargaining with the NFLU (30)
  - November and December, 1951, 3 (Reel 36)
    On Nov. 5, the Department of Labor wrote Mitchell to answer various questions he had submitted on the Mexican labor importation program; on Dec. 19, he sent the Department a memorandum on the changes the NFLU desired in the program. The Seventeenth Annual Convention was held in Memphis on December 8 and 9; the papers include the full proceedings, the Report of the National Executive Board, and the revised Constitution (Dec. 8). There is a letter from Mitchell to AFL President William Green suggesting possible AFL representatives for the new Farm Labor Advisory Council being set up by the Department of Labor (Nov. 19).
  - No Date, 1951, 4 (Reel 36)
    "Comments on the Migrant Labor Agreement of 1951" by Ernesto Galarza; a speech by Hank Hasiwar on California farm labor problems; "The Condition of Farm Workers in 1951", a report by NSF Executive Secretary Beth Biderman; an NFLU press release on the decision of Salinas lettuce growers to plow up half of their crop rather than submit to NFLU demands; and a letter from Galarza on the "wetback" problem
  - January and February, 1952, 5 (Reel 36)
    The main topic in the papers for these months is the hearings held by Senator Hubert H. Humphrey's Sub-Committee on Labor and Labor-Management Relations on legislation to implement the recommendations of the President's Commission on Migratory Labor. Materials of the President's Commission on Migratory Labor. Materials on this subject include information on the NFLU preparations for the hearings (Jan. 8 to 13), and statements by Louisiana strawberry farmer Lester Felder, California migrant workers Juanita Garcia and Hughe C. Williams, NFLU Vice-President F. R. Betton, Rev. Arthur C. Churchill, and organizer George Stith (Feb. 14). There is a letter from organizer Bill Becker on the latest developments in the dispute with the Schenley Co. (Jan 2), and a union press release on a wildcat strike by Schenley grape pickers at Delano, California (Jan. 10). The papers include a report by Galarza on "The Present Situation in the Imperial Valley" (Feb. 1), and a number of detailed letters from Hank Hasiwar, who had moved to Louisiana to organize strawberry farmers and began his stay with a highly successful two-day strike (Jan. 7; Feb 22, 25)
  - March and April, 1952, 6 (Reel 36)
    The Schenley Ranch at Delano, California laid off 100 workers, all NFLU members, and the union, claiming it was a lock-out, asked various AF of L Central Labor Councils to put Schenley products on the "unfair" list. The Schenley dispute may best be followed through the correspondence to and from Bill Becker, the NFLU organizer at Delano. There are three union press releases on the dispute (March 20, 25, 29). The papers include two detailed press releases, one from the Department of Labor and one from the union, on a meeting of the USES Federal Advisory Council which recommended that the Department conduct on-the-spot hearings on the availability of domestic labor before permitting the certification of foreign contract nationals (April 3,4)
  - May, 1952, 7 (Reel 36)
    A meeting took place on May 6 between Schenley officials and the union; for two distinctly different accounts of the meeting, see both a letter from the company to William Green and a report from organizer Bill Becker (7). There is also a report on the number of union members at the Schenley Ranch (1). AF of L Southern Director of Organization J.L. Rhodes served as a labor representative at the negotiations with Mexico on the renewal of the Migratory Labor Agreement; the papers include his formal report (23) and a copy of his personal report to William Green (20). There is an exchange between George Forstall, Secretary-Treasurer of the Louisiana Fruit and Vegetable Producers Union, and Mitchell over a Justice Department investigation to determine if the union's co-operative marketing scheme for strawberries violated the anti-trust laws (22, 28). Toward the end of the month, tension began to build once again in the Imperial Valley of California; see the correspondence from Galarza (26,29,31) and his report on the situation (24)
  - June to August, 1952, 8 (Reel 36)
    [Note: the union changed its name to the National Agricultural Workers Union (NAWU) as of June.] Due to an NAWU strike threat, the Department of Labor began a crackdown on the use of "wetbacks" and "braceros" in the Imperial Valley. The letters of a joyous Ernesto Galarza provide details on the union's victory, as does an NAWU press release (June 15). The union won a partial victory in the dispute with Schenley; Bill Becker reported the details of the agreement in a June 5 letter to AFL Central Unions. The NAWU strawberry growers in Louisiana staged some kind of strike action during June, but there is almost nothing about it in the papers except for a July 1 letter from organizer Hank Hasiwar. There is an interesting exchange between Mitchell and Hasiwar during August on plans to organize Louisiana sugar cane workers (9,19,20). The union also called a successful strike of melon-pickers at Los Banos, California which resulted in the deportation of 300 wetbacks; see the letters from Galarza (Aug. 25 and n.d. [August]) and a press release (Aug. 23). Finally, there is a list of workers sent by the NAWU Mid-South office to the H.J. Heinz Co. in Salem, NJ for seasonal work (Aug. 3)
  - September and October, 1952, 9 (Reel 36)
    The main topic during September is Francisco Cano, a Mexican contract worker sent to Washington by Galarza to complain to the Mexican Ambassador about his exploitation at the hands of California growers. Details on the Cano mission appear in the correspondence of Galarza and in an NAWU press release (Sept 9). Readers interested in the union's work with strawberry farmers in Louisiana might consult a two-page narrative by Mitchell on the background and current operations of the Louisiana Fruit and Vegetable Producers Union (Oct 7). Thre was a very important meeting of the NAWU National Executive Board held in Louisiana on October 24 and 25; the papers include the minutes and a set of resolutions which set forth the future plans of the union
  - November and December, 1952, 10 (Reel 36)
    The October meeting of the National Executive Board decided on several drastic changes in the union's operations, among them the closing down of the NAWU office in Fresno, California and the firing of Fresno organizer William Swearingen, who had allegedly permitted Communists to join his local. The papers for November and December are full of long, philosophical letters between Mitchell and his key organizers (Galarza, Hasiwar, and Becker) on the shake-up and on the NAWU's future strategy. There is also a set of notes by Galarza setting forth the pros and cons of the Department of Labor's plan to fix the prevailing wages of braceros (Nov. 19) and his five-page statement on the practice of deducting the cost of tie-wires (Twistems) from the wages of carrot tiers (Dec. 5). Finally, the union filed claims with the Department of Agriculture for the unpaid wages of 392 Louisiana sugar cane workers; see two letters from Hank Hasiwar to the Department (Nov. 3,6) and a NAWU press release on this subject (Dec 17). The Department's reply appears on April 10, 1953
  - No date, 1952, 11 (Reel 36)
    Notes on Farm Workers -- 1952, a sketch by Mitchell sent to the NSF; an outline by Galarza for his Spring, 1952 campaign in the Imperial Valley; a 12-page report by Hank Hasiwar on "Wages and Working Conditions of Sugar Cane workers on Louisiana Plantations"; Supplemental Statement by the NFLU submitted to the Senate Subcommittee on Labor and Labor-Management Relations; a 27-page statement by Galarza on "The Operation and Effects of the International Executive Agreement of 1951 For the Recruitment and Employment of Mexican Nationals in Agriculture in the U.S."
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1952, 12 (Reel 36)
    Folder 1317 -- List of workers sent to H.J. Heinz Co., 1952.
- January 1953 to December 1953, Undated 1953, and January 1954 to February 1954. (Reel 37)